So, we know we need to create layouts
and assets optimized for different screen pixel densities
and sizes. So, now's a great time to
introduce you to the Android resource framework. All externalized
Android resources, everything from strings to layouts to
drawables and animations are all stored within your project's
res folder. You've already been putting your strings
in the strings.xml file stored in the values folder.
And you've been putting your layouts into the layout
folder. And you know to reference your resources using
at notation within both your xml or within the
code. And then at runtime, Android will insert the
appropriate resource for you. So far, so good. And
here's where things get a little more interesting. Android
allows you to create alternative versions of every resource
by placing them into folders with different qualifiers. We separate
each of those using a hyphen. And we can
add those qualifiers based on anything from language and
or dialect to whether the device is docked, the
type of touch screen, the pixel density of the
display, the orientation of the screen, and most importantly
for a responsive design in particular, the smallest available
screen width which you can support with that layout.
At runtime, Android will check the count device configuration,
it's language, it's screen size, pixel density, everything,
and then load the right layout strings and drawables
accordingly. You can even chain these qualifiers together. For
example, to create a different layout for German language
users to account for all of those really long
German words, or more typically for a combination of
screen size and device configuration. Now, keep in mind
that many of these values can change at runtime.
The most common change being that of orientation. And
it's for this reason that Android activities are destroyed
and recreated whenever the device configuration changes. And that's
because the layout and all of the resources within it
could be completely different based on something as simple
as screen orientation change. Now it's good practice, as
well, to localize your apps and provide translated strings
for all of your users using this mechanism. And that's
a task made a lot easier. Thanks to Google
Play Publisher site that can offer you this service. It's
also a really good idea to provide different drawables
at the appropriate pixel density, so you can get a
nice crisp image on every device. And when it
comes to providing alternative layouts, Android has gone through a
few alternative models. Starting in the early days, with this
screen buckets idea of small, normal large, and extra large.
But, since Android 3.2, the new smallest width qualifier has
given us much more fine grain control over our layouts.